University of Connecticut 1995.0018
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, Child Development Laboratories Records
undated, 1961-1991.
1995.0018
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
4.0 Linear feet
The Child Development Laboratories (CDL) are part of the School of Family Studies and serve the university, community and state as a model demonstration laboratory center.
University of Connecticut, Child Development Laboratories.
History
University records indicate that programs for young children existed during the 1940s, however the documentation is minimal. In 1961, the "Nursery School" that had existed until then, experienced a name change to the "Preschool Laboratory." At that time, the program consisted of two half-day sessions with eighteen three and four year olds per session and was housed in a building on the site of what is now the Fine Arts Complex.
In 1968, the Preschool Laboratory moved to the newsly constructed Human Development Center. Only two classroom suites were utilized; one room housed the two half-day sessions and the other functioned as a creative experience laboratory. The 1970s saw a growing national demand for child "day care centers." The demand was spurred by increases in the numbers of married students with children, employed women, and young professionals. Programs for young children were no longer viewed as a luxusry but rather as a necessity.
A proposal was written in 1973 to establish a day care center in the Human Development Center. The Department of Public Works, however, rejected the request for additional funding and facilities and the program continued as a preschool laboratory. In 1974, a committee of parents was organized and exerted pressure on the Unviersity administration to change the preschool Laboratories to a day care facility with expanded hours and extended age-ranges. Although uninterested in the concept of "day care," the University was interested in the philosophy of a "child development laboratory," emphasizing the stimulation and enrichment of children's growth and development. The Child Development Laboratories (CDL) was formally established by the University on 26 January 1976.
In 1976, the CDL maintained one full-day infant/toddler program, one full-day preschool program and two half-day preschool programs. Due to low demand and economic unfeasibility, the half-day programs were eliminated in 1981, and the CDL format evolved to support full-day programs for infant/toddlers, preschool and kindergarten.
The Child Development Laboratories are part of the School of Family Studies and serve the university, community and state as a model demonstration laboratory center. The CDL is licensed by the state of Connecticut and accredited by the National Academy of Early Childhood Programs. Programs for 100 children age six weeks to six years are offered through the CDL as a function of its role as a setting for teaching, training and research in early childhood education and development. The major goals of the CDL are training students, conducting research and services for children.
Information on additional initiatives concerning child care at the University is also available.
Note: Information for this history was provided by materials in the collection. More recent information on the CDL and its programs s available on the CDL website.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials relevant to the establishment of child care facilities on the Storrs campus of the University, as well as documentation of the early years of the CDL.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one alphabetic series.
Series I: Records ( undated, 1961-1991 ).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred to the University Archives in 1995.
University of Connecticut.; Administrative Records.; Child development--Connecticut.; Child development--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Connecticut--Education--Universities and colleges.; Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Publications.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)--Education--Universities and colleges.; Universities and colleges--Connecticut--Administration.; University of Connecticut. Child Development Laboratories.
- Series I: Records, undated, 1961-1991
  - Brochure, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Committee for Child Care, undated, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Comprehensive Child Care Act, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Construction--Color and Finish Selection, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Construction--Room numbers and function, undated, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Construction--Specifications for Renovations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence--University, 1981-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and support for child care at UConn, 1971-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Daily Record of activity (blank), undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Financial information, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Forms letters, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - History, undated, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Infant Center, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Information for the parents of..., 1961-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Newsclippings, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter--notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Nursery School sign, undated (Box 3)
  - Parent Advisory Board, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Parent responses, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Policy--Admissions, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Policy--Handbook, undated (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Policy--Health and accident, undated (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Politics of Child Care Conference, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Pre-School History and fees, 1962-1968 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Proposal--Child Care Center, pre 1974-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Proposal--Child Care at UMass, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Proposal--Committee for Child Care, undated (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Proposal-- Hazen Foundation, 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Rehabilitation of the Physically handicapped, 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Report--ACTION, 1976-1977 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - Report--Child Care UConn, 1974-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - Report--UConnPIRG on Daycare in Connecticutu, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
  - Report-- University Senate on Child Care, 1972-1973 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - State Regulations, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - State Regulations, 1977 (Box 2:, Folder 35)